#### Contact

+7-9213882934 (Mobile) samehome@yandex.ru

www.linkedin.com/in/alesavin (LinkedIn) alesavin.ru (Personal)

### Top Skills

Java

Big Data

**Functional Programming** 

### Languages

Russian (Native or Bilingual) English (Professional Working)

#### Certifications

Machine Learning

Principles of Reactive Programming

Big Data Analysis with Scala and Spark

Functional Programming Principles in Scala

Certified Reactive Architect

# **Alex Savin**

Lead Software Engineer at EPAM Systems

Andalusia

## Summary

More than 10 years of experience at software development: started from DevOps role to team leader. I joined Yandex. Classifieds infrastructure (Saint Petersburg, Russia) in 2011, my core points there were: Java/Scala development, highload architectures, distributed systems for big data/stream processing (Hadoop/Kafka/Spark), search and near topics. At the start of 2019, I relocated to Malaga, Spain, initially in favor of Ciklum project with a strong passion for functional programming and now I have a warm welcome at EPAM with wider opportunities. I like to build high-quality systems according to The Reactive Manifesto and invest in coaching others to make wonderful things together.

## Experience

**EPAM Systems** 

Lead Software Engineer

January 2020 - Present (1 year 2 months)

Málaga Area, Spain

#### Ciklum

Senior Scala Developer

February 2019 - January 2020 (1 year)

Málaga Area, Spain

My project was related to gambling area. I developed event-based microservices for sport-betting industry at small team with platform duties. Mostly DDD, reactive and functional programming.

#### Yandex

7 years 10 months

Senior Software Developer Team Lead

November 2015 - January 2019 (3 years 3 months)

Saint Petersburg, Russian Federation

I lead group of developers with designing, developing and support backend for quality and commercial platforms, deal with software tasks at infrastructure Page 1 of 3

team of vertical searches business unit. Prefer reactive programming patterns and Scala/Akka technology stack.

#### Software Developer

April 2011 - December 2015 (4 years 9 months)

Saint Petersburg, Russian Federation

Developing Java, Scala services for vertical search on car ads, vacancies and realty offers. In details: 2-4 mln entities depends on service, >1000 partner feeds, fault-tolerant ETL (extract, transform, load) process include feed downloading, data sharding, unification, clusterization, index building, index update on 64 search machines. Hadoop/HBase for statistical tasks, MySQL for analytics. Team share tasks on services for the best replaceability.

Figures: full index update over 15 min, fast search 4000rps 99.9% < 50ms, detailed search 500rps 99% < 500ms.

Technologies: Scala/Akka/Spray, Lucene, Cassandra, HBase, MySQL.

#### Favor-IT

5 years 2 months

#### DevOps

April 2008 - April 2011 (3 years 1 month)

Developing, managing and deploying software for water analysis. Full process from workspace organization to production release: infrastructure tasks (VCS/IDE, CI, fault- tolerant network, phone support system, monitoring), hardware selection and installation (common/blade servers, RAID, SuSE linux, network), software development (Java EE, EJB, Servlets, JSP), deploy (self-developed system), product support. Lead (include hiring) personnel of infrastructure group (2 people max).

Technologies: Linux, Java EE, Tomcat, PostgreSQL, Ant.

#### System Engineer

March 2006 - March 2008 (2 years 1 month)

Managing server farm for the SaaS solution (water analisys). Figures: 2 data centers, >60 machines, >20 services (10-100 users each), SuSE Linux, RAID, fault-tolerant network. Manage emergency switch to slave services or backups (1h outage max).

#### **BizHost**

System Engineer

July 2005 - December 2005 (6 months)

Web hosting, mail hosting. FreeBSB- based virtual hosting with self-developed panel (PHP, MySQL), dedicated hosting. Figures: >10000 sites, 10 machines.

# Education

Saint Petersburg State Polytechnical University

Master of Science, Computer Science · (2005 - 2006)

Saint Petersburg State Polytechnical University Bachelor's degree, Computer Science · (1999 - 2004)